[MUSIC PLAYING]
[Nhạc dạo]
Friends, Viruses, and Other Forms of Cooperation.
Bạn bè, virus, và các dạng hợp tác khác.
Well, one of the most controversial parts of this
Vâng, một trong những phần gây tranh cãi nhất của
theory of endosymbiosis was that some of the change in
thuyết nội cộng sinh đó là một số thay dổi trong
organisms wasn't just the result of mutations or
các sinh vật không chỉ là kết quả của  đột biến hoặc
alterations in the genetic material in the process of
những thay đổi trong vật liệu di truyền trong quá trình
reproduction.
sinh sản.
The idea was that new genetic material could actually be
Ý tưởng rằng vật liệu di truyền có thể thật sự
inserted into the nucleus either by a virus or a
được đưa vào nhân tế vào bởi virus hoặc
bacteria by a different process.
vi khuẩn bởi một quá trình khác.
It didn't just arise by mutation.
Nó không chỉ xuất hiện bởi đột biến.
Now in fact, new research has been done that starts to bear
Thật ra hiện giờ, nghiên cứu mới được thực hiện bắt đầu chứng minh
this controversial part of the theory out.
phần gây tranh cãi của giả thuyết này là đúng.
We now realise that even single-celled organisms can
Giờ ta nhận ra rằng thậm chí những sinh vật đơn bào cũng có thể
sometimes pass DNA laterally from one to another.
đôi khi truyền DNA theo hướng ngang từ sinh vật này sang sinh vật khác.
You don't just get-- well, the bacteria don't just get their
Bạn không chỉ có được- vi khuẩn không chỉ đơn giản nhận được
genetic material from their parent.
vật liệu di truyền từ cha mẹ chúng.
Bacteria can pass DNA from one to the other.
Vi khuẩn có thể truyền DNA từ vi khuẩn này sang vi khuẩn khác.
They can steal DNA a from each other.
Chúng có thể đánh cắp DNA từ nhau.
This helps us to understand a whole series of evolutionary
Điều này giúp chúng ta hiểu một loạt những biến cố về tiến hóa,
events, including the rise of sexual reproduction.
bao gồm sự xuất hiện của sự sinh sản hữu tính.
But perhaps the most startling discovery that's related to
Nhưng có lẽ khám phá gây ngạc nhiên nhất có liên quan đến
this theory is that large amounts of DNA are actually
giả thiết này đó là có những lượng lớn DNA thật ra được để lại
left over from viruses.
bởi virus.
They're called retroviruses.
Chúng được gọi là retrovirus.
They insert themselves into the germ cells, into
Chúng tự gài mình vào tế bào mầm, vào
the sperm and eggs.
tinh trùng và trứng.
And even in our human genome, a lot of the material actually
Và thậm chí trong bộ gien người, rất nhiều vật liệu thật sự
turns out to be retroviruses.
hóa ra là retrovirus.
Now to understand how this works, I have to explain a
Giờ để hiểu cách vận hành của điều này, tôi phải giải thích một
little bit about retroviruses.
chút về retrovirus.
A retrovirus is a little bit of RNA.
Retrovirus là một chút RNA.
That's the simpler, single-sided version of DNA.
Đó là phiên bản đơn giản hơn, một mặt của DNA.
Now what it will do is it will actually insert itself into a
Điều nó sẽ làm là nó sẽ thật sự tự gắn mình vào
gene, into a DNA molecule.
gien, vào một phân tử DNA.
And then it kind of does the reverse of
Và sau đó nó đảo ngược
what DNA usually does.
những gì DNA thường làm.
It'll actually regenerate the other side.
Nó thật sự tái tạo mặt còn lại.
And in the process, sits itself right
Và trong quá trình này, nó lại ở ngay trong
into the DNA molecule.
phân tử DNA.
That's your retrovirus.
Đó là retrovirus.
This is the retrovirus's way of getting reproduced.
Đây là cách sinh sản của retrovirus.
Some of them are incredibly dangerous.
Một số trong số chúng cực kỳ nguy hiểm.
The HIV virus, for example, is a retrovirus.
Virus HIV, chẳng hạn, là retrovirus.
And they can even cause the death of the animal.
Và chúng thậm chí có thể gây ra cái chết của động vật.
Some cancers we think might even be retroviruses.
Một số bệnh ung thư ta nghĩ có thể thậm chí là các retrovirus.
But some less virulent forms of retroviruses can actually
Nhưng một số dạng retrovirus ít độc hại hơn có thể thật sự
become endogenous.
trở nên nội sinh.
That is, they sort of stitch themselves into the DNA, not
Tức là, chúng tự cài mình vào DNA, không chỉ
just of the body cells, but of those germ line cells, that is
của tế bào cơ thể, mà còn vào những tế bào mầm, tức là
the sperm and eggs, the parts of the organisms that the
trứng và tinh trùng, những phần của sinh vật mà
early 20th century geneticists thought
các nhà di truyền học đầu thế kỷ 20 đã nghĩ là
that couldn't be changed.
không thể bị  thay đổi.
They hack their way in.
Chúng xâm nhập vào.
And they become a permanent part of the DNA, passed on to
Và chúng trở thành một phần cố định của DNA, được truyền sang
the next generations.
những thế hệ sau.
In big, multicelled organisms like human beings, it turns
Trong những sinh vật đa bào lớn như con người, hóa ra
out there's a tonne of these old retroviruses lying around.
có cả tấn những retrovirus này khắp nơi.
In fact, in our DNA it looks like there's 100,000 sections
Thật ra trong DNA nó có vẻ như có 100,000 vùng
that are retroviral insertions.
là retrovirus cài vào.
They have been put in by retroviruses.
Chúng đã được đưa vào bởi retrovirus.
As much as 8% of all of our DNA turns out to look like it
Khoảng 8% trong tổng số DNA của chúng ta hóa ra có vẻ như
has this kind of viral origin.
có nguồn gốc từ virus.
Some of these retroviruses can still flare up.
Một trong số những retrovirrus này vẫn có thể phát ra lại.
We think for example that some of the autoimmune diseases may
Chẳng hạn chúng ta nghĩ rằng một số bệnh tự miễn dịch có thể
have their origin in this kind of genetic material.
có nguồn gốc xuất xứ từ loại vật liệu di truyền này.
But in some cases, the retroviruses have become sort
Nhưng trong một số trường hợp, retrovirus đã trở thành
of innocuous.
vô hại.
We even use them for useful purposes.
Chúng ta thậm chí còn dùng chúng cho những mục đích có ích.
In fact, endogenous retroviruses are responsible
Thật ra, retrovirus vô hại đã tạo ra
for the placenta that's essential to all mammals.
nhau thai thiết yếu cho những động vật có vú.
The placenta protects the infant, protects the embryo
Nhau thai bảo vệ trẻ sơ sinh, bảo vệ phôi thai
against the mother's immune system.
khỏi hệ miễn dịch của người mẹ.
But it also latches on to the mother's body and draws out
Nhưng nó còn gắn với cơ thể người mẹ và lấy ra
nutrients for the embryo.
chất dinh dưỡng cho bào thai.
If the ancestors of mammals hadn't caught this retrovirus,
Nếu tổ tiên của các động vật có vú không bị nhiễm retrovirus này,
we wouldn't have placentas.
ta sẽ không có nhau thai.
And that would mean that we would have to
Và điều đó có nghĩa là ta vẫn phải
still be laying eggs.
đẻ trứng.
The point is that none of this really undermines
Vấn đề là không có gì trong điều này thật sự làm suy yếu
evolutionary theory.
thuyết tiến hóa.
Endosymbiosis, and endogenous retroviruses, what they really
Thuyết nội cộng sinh, và các retrovirus nội sinh, thật sự giúp chúng ta
help us explain is that there are other ways that variation
giải thích rằng có những cách khác mà sự thay đổi có thể xuất hiện,
can arise, other than just mutation.
thay vì chỉ có đột biến.
And fitness isn't just fitness for competition.
Và sự phù hợp không chỉ là phù hợp để cạnh tranh
Fitness may be fitness for cooperation.
Sự phù hợp có thể là phù hợp để hợp tác.
A living thing may actually find it's niche inside another
Một sinh vật sống thật sự` có thể tìm thấy kẽ hở cho nó bên trong cơ thể
living thing.
một sinh vật khác.
And in the process, if it makes its host more viable, it
Và trong quá trình này, nếu nó làm cho vật chủ của mình có thể sống được hơn,
actually creates more of the niche
nó sẽ thật sự tạo ra một kẽ hở lớn hơn
that it needs to survive.
cần thiết để tồn tại.
Perhaps, the most striking example of this kind of
Có lẽ, ví dụ đáng kinh ngạc nhất về loại hợp tác này
cooperation is in animals that we refer to as eusocial.
nằm ở các động vật có tính xã hội đầy đủ.
Eusocial animals, like bees and termites and ants, a large
Các động vật có tính xã hội đầy đủ, như ong, mối và kiến, có một tỷ lệ lớn
percentage of them are sterile.
là vô sinh.
That is in an ant colony or a bee colony, there's a large
Tức là trong một đàn kiến hoặc một đàn ong, có một số lượng lớn
number of workers who will never reproduce.
các con thợ không bao giờ sinh sản.
A question is how could that possibly be an adaptation of
Có một câu hỏi là làm thế nào điều đó lại có thể là một sự thích nghi của tiến hóa,
evolution, if you can't even pass on your DNA in any way?
nếu bạn thậm chí không thể truyền lại DNA?
We realise now the key to understanding phenomena like
Ta nhận ra rằng chìa khóa để hiểu những hiện tượng như
eusocietality, is actually inclusive fitness.
quần thể mang tính chất xã hội đầy đủ, thật ra là inclusive fitness.
Inclusive fitness is the idea that we don't just pass on the
Inclusive fitness là ý tưởng rằng ta không chỉ trao truyền
DNA that comes directly from our own bodies, but in some
DNA trực tiếp từ cơ thể của chúng ta, mà trong một số trường hợp
cases we pass on DNA through the support
ta còn truyền lại DNA qua sự hỗ trợ của ta
we give to our siblings.
đối với các anh em ruột của mình.
That is if we share a lot of DNA with our siblings, one of
Tức là nếu ta chia sẻ nhiều DNA với anh em ruột của mình, một trong
the things that we can do to help our DNA get passed on is
những việc mà ta có thể làm để giúp cho DNA của chúng ta được truyền lại đó là
actually to support them.
thật sự giúp đỡ họ.
Inclusive fitness is one way to explain phenomena like
Inclusive fitness là một cách để giải thích các hiện tượng như
altruism, which at first glance don't seem
sự vị tha, điều mà ban đầu có vẻ
to make much sense.
không có lý lắm.
If you help individuals who share a lot of DNA with
Nếu bạn giúp những cá nhân có nhiều DNA giống với
yourself, that can actually be a way that you become more
bạn, điều đó có thể thật sự là cách để bạn trở nên có khả năng
likely to pass on your DNA to future generations.
trao truyền DNA của bạn cho các thế hệ tương lai.
Another possibility, related but a bit more controversial,
Một khả năng khác, có liên quan nhưng gây tranh cãi hơn,
is the idea that what may be happening is
đó là sự thật có thể là
actually group selection.
sự chọn lọc theo nhóm.
That is, instead of the individuals competing one
Tức là, thay vì các cá thể cạnh tranh với nhau,
against another, it's one group of a species against
thì một nhóm của loài này cạnh tranh với một nhóm khác
another group of the same species.
thuộc cùng loài đó.
It's one termite colony against
Đó là một đàn mối cạnh tranh với
another termite colony.
một đàn mối khác.
If resources are tight and groups can secure them better,
Nếu các nguồn lực eo hẹp và các nhóm có thể giữ gìn chúng tốt hơn,
then it may be the case that actually there's different
then it may be the case that actually there's different
levels of selection.
levels of selection.
Again, this is controversial.
Again, this is controversial.
But some theorists talk about how selection actually
But some theorists talk about how selection actually
operates at the genetic level, at the individual level, and
operates at the genetic level, at the individual level, and
possibly even at the group level.
possibly even at the group level.
Arguably, humans have benefited from extraordinary
Arguably, humans have benefited from extraordinary
forms of cooperation.
forms of cooperation.
From a very small population 100,000 years ago, precarious,
From a very small population 100,000 years ago, precarious,
maybe even on the verge of extinction in some moments, we
maybe even on the verge of extinction in some moments, we
have grown to cover the planet.
have grown to cover the planet.
And we've done that through some extraordinary forms of
And we've done that through some extraordinary forms of
cooperation and even symbiosis.
cooperation and even symbiosis.
Today, the total body mass of all the humans on the planet
Today, the total body mass of all the humans on the planet
is eight times the mass of all the other wild
is eight times the mass of all the other wild
vertebrates on land.
vertebrates on land.
In fact, the total mass of humans is equal to all of the
In fact, the total mass of humans is equal to all of the
whales and fish in the sea combined.
whales and fish in the sea combined.
Our domestic animals, our cows and our pigs and our dogs
Our domestic animals, our cows and our pigs and our dogs
together, weigh more than 20 times what wild animals weigh.
together, weigh more than 20 times what wild animals weigh.
And together, us and our herds, make up a quarter of
And together, us and our herds, make up a quarter of
the weight of all living things on the planet.
the weight of all living things on the planet.
We're even shaping each other's evolution.
We're even shaping each other's evolution.
We're co-evolving with our domesticated animals.
We're co-evolving with our domesticated animals.
It's pretty amazing that in the space of 6,000
It's pretty amazing that in the space of 6,000
generations, we've gone from being just one species to
generations, we've gone from being just one species to
being this kind of dominant species.
being this kind of dominant species.
We have changed the environment.
We have changed the environment.
We're changing the planet.
We're changing the planet.
But it's not the first time it's happened.
But it's not the first time it's happened.
After all, you're breathing the evidence of
After all, you're breathing the evidence of
these kinds of changes.
these kinds of changes.
In this module, we started with Darwin's basic theory of
In this module, we started with Darwin's basic theory of
natural selection.
natural selection.
And we've shown how we've developed it, improved it, but
And we've shown how we've developed it, improved it, but
how it essentially remains unchanged.
how it essentially remains unchanged.
In the next module, we're going to be talking about sex,
In the next module, we're going to be talking about sex,
sex selection, reproduction, how it helps to shape our
sex selection, reproduction, how it helps to shape our
species and how our babies are one of the most important
species and how our babies are one of the most important
things for determining how we become human.
things for determining how we become human.